Guide to the Commission on Christian Higher Education Research Project Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
Commission on Christian Higher Education Research Project records
1951-1958
RG 231
Yale University Divinity School Library
1.5
(3 boxes)
These papers document the "What is a Christian College?" Research Study Project conducted by the Commission on Christian Higher Education of the Association of American Colleges, in association with the National Council of Churches. The papers include workshop information, summaries of workshop results, research study progress reports from participating colleges, manuscripts of book chapters intended for publication, and correspondence regarding the research study, workshops, and manuscripts.
Association of American Colleges. Commission on Christian Higher Education. Research Committee
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
According to a 1952 published report titled The Consolidated Report of the Six Faculty Workshops of 1952 in the Research Study Project "What is a Christian College?" the project was undertaken in the early 1950s under the supervision of the Research Committee of the Commission on Christian Higher Education of the Association of American Colleges, directed by Dr. Raymond F. McLain of the National Council of Churches. The project received financial support from the Lilly Endowment, Inc. President Clyde A. Milner of Guilford College was chairman of the Research Committee. The other members were Philip E. Dion, John W. Hollenbach, F.E. Johnson, W. Hugh McEniry, Jr., Roland G. Simonitsch, Harlie L. Smith, Andrew G. Truxal, and Walter E. Wiest. Mr. M. C. Ballenger of Yale served as editorial secretary of the project during the summer of 1952, which is probably why these files were found in storage at the Yale Divinity Library.
Representatives of thirty-six colleges participated in the first workshop of the project, held in August of 1951 at Berea College, Kentucky. One hundred ninety-two colleges were represented in the six workshops of 1952, held at Earlham College, Cedar Crest College, Mars Jill Junior College, Drake University, St. Mary's University, and Occidental College. Most of the faculty members comprising the workshops had served as chairs of their own campus study committee. Most of the college had circulated two preliminary working reports to the other colleges in their area.
. The 1952 published report indicated that the continuing institutions would submit two progress reports to the director of the study during the school year 1952-1953. These reports would be circulated to the participating colleges "for their mutual benefit and stimulation." It was expected that the final over-all report of the project would be in the form a a volume on the nature and role for the Christian college available in the fall of 1953. In 1958 the What is a Christian college?: A revision of the Consolidated Report of the Research Study Project prepared by Raymond F. McLain, 1952 report, edited by David B Sageser, was published by the Commission on Higher Education of the National Council of Churches.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains reports from the schools that were participating in the "What is a Christian College" study project as well as correspondence and manuscripts from efforts to incorporate the results of the research study a final report.
Series I, Organization and Workshops includes information regarding the initiation of the research study, the colleges that participated in the research study, and Secretary's reports and summaries describing the results of the workshops.
Series II, Research Study Progress Reports by Participating Colleges are arranged alphabetically by college name. The progress reports were created by committees established by each college to consider the research question, "What is a Christian College?"
Series III, Correspondence and Manuscripts documents the efforts to write a book stemming from the research study project and workshops. There is correspondence with contributing chapter authors, publishers, and editors who worked on the manuscript. The manuscript in various stages is also included.
Arrangement
I. Organization and Workshops, 1951-1952
II. Research Study Progress Reports by Participating Colleges, 1952-1953
III. Correspondence and Manuscripts, 1953-1958
College students -- Religious life; Universities and colleges -- Religion; Association of American Colleges. Commission on Christian Higher Education. Research Committee
- Organization and Workshops, 1951-1952; Series I
  - "What is a Christian College?" Research Project Workshop at Berea College, 27-31 Aug 1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "What is a Christian College?" Research Project Workshops, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "What is a Christian College?" Research Project Workshops, Secretary's Reports, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "What is a Christian College?" Research Project Workshops, Summary of Summer Workshops, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Research Study Progress Reports by Participating Colleges, 1952-1953; Series II
  - A - Adrian College, Albion College, Augustana College, Aurora College, Austin College, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - B - Baker University, Baldwin Wallace College, Beaver College, Bessie Tift College, Bethany College, Bethel College, Bloomfield College, Bowdoin College, Bucknell University, Buena Vista College, Butler College, Butler University, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - C - Campbell College, Campbellsville College, Capital University, Carroll College, Carthage College, Catawba College, Centenary College, Central College (Iowa), Central College (Missouri), Centre College of Kentucky, Chapman College, Claremont Men's College, Coe College, College of the Holy Cross, College of St. Mary of the Springs, College of Saint Teresa, Colorado Woman's College, Columbia College, Concordia College, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - D - Denison University, Depauw University, Dickinson College, Doane College, Drew University, Drury College, Dunbarton College of Holy Cross, D'Youville College, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - E - Elmhurst College, Emory & Henry College, Episcopal College of the Southwest, Eureka College, Evansville College, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - F - Flora MacDonald College, Florida Normal and Industrial Memorial College, Franklin and Marshall College, Franklin College, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - G - Getttysburg College, Greensboro College, Guilford College, Gustavus Adolphus College, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - H - Hanover College, Harding College, Hardin-Simmons University, Harwick College, Hastings College, Heidelberg College, High Point College, Hiram College, Huntington College, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - I-K - Indiana Central, Jamestown College, Juniata College, Kalamazoo College, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - L - La Verne College, Lebanon Valley College, Lees-McRae College, Lincoln University, Louisberg College, Loyola University of Los Angeles, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - M - Macalester College, MacMurray College for Women, McPherson College, Madison College, Manchester College, Marian College, Marion College, Mars Hill College, Maryville College, Maryville College of the Sacred Heart, Millsaps College, Millikin University, Mitchell College, Monmouth College, Montreat College, Moravian College, Morningside College, Mount Union College, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - N - Newberry College, Newton College of Sacred Heart, North Central College, North Park College, Northwest Nazarene College, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - O - Occidental College, Otterbein College, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - P - Pacific Lutheran College, Pacific Union College, Park College, Parsons College, Pasadena College, Philander Smith College, Pikeville College, Presbyterian College, Presbyterian Junior College, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - R - Reinhardt College, Ricks College, Rosary College, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - S - Sacred Heart Dominican College, Saint Augustine's College, St. Joseph College, St. Joseph's College, St. Mary's College, St. Olaf College, Salem College, Shaw University, Shenandoah College and Conservatory of Music, Shorter College, Johnson C. Smith University, Southwestern University, Spring Arbor Junior College, Susquehanna University, Sweet Briar College, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - T - Talladega College, Texas Lutheran College, Thiel College, Tougaloo College, Trinity University, Tusculum College, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - U - University of Corpus Christi, University of Dubuque, University of Notre Dame, Upsala College, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - V - Valparaiso University, Virginia Intermont College, Virginia State College, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - W - Waldorf College, Walla Walla College, Wartburg College, Washington Missionary College, West Virginia Wesleyan, Westmar College, Westminster College (Missouri), Westminster College (Utah), Wiley College, William Jewell College, William Penn College, William Woods College, Wilmington College, Wittenberg College, Wofford College, 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - X-Z - Young Harris College, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Correspondence and Manuscripts, 1953-1958; Series III
  - Correspondence regarding Nature and Role of the Christian College, Dr. Raymond F. McLain, 1953-1955 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence regarding manuscript - What is a Christian College?, 1955-1958 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Manuscript - Chapters by Dirks, Hollenbeck, & McEniery, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Report of the Workshop - What is a Christian College?, Nov 1957 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Manuscript - What is a Christian College? and Correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Manuscript - What is a Christian College?, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 8)